Good morning. Today's daf is קכג Kuf-Chaf-Gimel 123 and we pick up
where are five lines
down
איתיבי. Eitivei. Actually right the topic of discussion the issue of discussion
is is that the Mishna mentioned that you can use a hammer
to crack nuts and a saw to cut cheese and it's basically
the principle of כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur that a vessel
that is used normally for prohibited use can be used לצורך גופו
l'tzorech gufo can be used to do for you know use the
object itself for some permissible purpose. I mean the question is what
else would you use it for? You wouldn't use it for a
forbidden purpose but לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo is to contrast to two
other possibilities which we'll see later today. One is לצורך מקומו l'tzorech
mekomo you're not actually using the object you just need its space
you need to move it out of the way. And the other
is מחמה לצל. mechama l'tzel. מחמה לצל mechama l'tzel means you're doing
it that you're getting it out of the sun into the shade
you're doing it to protect it. But here you're actually using it
for a for use for a legitimate use is that allowed? And
the Mishna seemed very clear that it was. But actually there was
somewhat of a debate because Rav Yehuda wanted to explain the Mishna
in very limited terms and say that it was only talking about
a vessel that was designated for a היתר heter use which would
seem quite against the whole point of the Mishna. So and to
that Rava argued and said no the whole point of the Mishna
is that even for forbidden use if it's made for forbidden use
you can use it for permissible use on Shabbat. So let's just
let's finish this discussion. So the Gemara says like this איתיבי Eitivei
so again it is five lines down from the top last word
on the line איתיבי Eitivei I'll ask you בית שמאי אומרים Beit
Shammai omrim we'll read the parentheses it whatever whether it's there or
not it gives the background of this of this regardless. So בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says אין נוטלין את העלי לקצבה עליו בשר ein
notlin et ha-ali liktzava alav basar you do not take the pestle
which is the you know big thing that you bang spices with
but it apparently was wide and large and it could be used
just like an as an ad hoc cutting board. So on יום
טוב Yom Tov you don't you don't crush spices on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Actually it's an interesting question why you don't because it's
לצורך אוכל נפש l'tzorech ochel nefesh and there's actually questions about under
certain circumstances you can crush spices on יום טוב Yom Tov but
let's bracket that for now. We're assuming that generally you can't use
this but the question is can you use it as a cutting
board? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you cannot ובית הלל מתירים
u'Veit Hillel matirin and Beit Hillel allow it ושוין שאם קצב עליו
בשר ve-shavin she-im katzav alav basar but they agree that if you
did cut meat on it like after you're done using it to
cut meat שאסור לטלטלו she-assur letaltelo that you can't move it because
even בית הלל Beit Hillel is only allowing you for the sake
of שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov to cut your meat use
it to cut your meat but any other point even בית הלל
Beit Hillel would forbid you to move it. So why are you
forbidden to move it? At worst it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli
shemelachto l'issur and you should be allowed to use it move it
if you've got a purpose for it according to Rava according to
the read of the the straightforward read of the Mishna.
But it doesn't mean that when you're done then then it becomes
still כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur just like I
use a hammer for nuts? I know so that's then
then I'm done cracking nuts then I still can't use it?
No so the understanding though is that the language is you can't
use it for any purpose that we only allowed you to use
it for cutting meat for special שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov
היתר heter but any other purpose it's forbidden. So why is that?
So סבר לשינויי ליה כרבי נחמיה savar leshinuyei lei k'Rabbi Nechemia he
thought he would answer him like Rabbi Nechemia which is what the
answer he gave yesterday. This is like the answer to have in
the back of your pocket because we're going to see tomorrow that
Rabbi Nechemia in the Mishna says that he's extremely restrictive. Forget כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur forget that. He says anything you want
to use on Shabbat you can only use לצורך תשמישו l'tzorech tashmisho
what it's normally made for. So for example if I have a
fork I can use it for eating my food but I can't
use it for I don't know for like scratching myself with it.
You know totally היתר heter but it's not what a fork is
made for. You know anything I want to use I can only
use for the classic thing it's made for no other purpose because
that's presumably the use I had in mind when Shabbat began so
no other use. So Rabbi Nechemia is extremely restrictive right even כלי
שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter you can only use it exactly for
its intended purpose. So if you have a have a ברייתא braita
that is restrictive and sounds like it has a broader sense of
מוקצה muktzah or Mishna whatever you know a good answer is to
say oh that's Rabbi Nechemia. Rabbi Nechemia doesn't really let you use
anything for anything that it's you know for for something that it's
not its intended use. So that's what Rava thought to say that
this is all within the position of Rabbi Nechemia. That though would
be pretty interesting if both בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל
Beit Hillel held like Rabbi Nechemia. Anyway כיון דשמעה להא דאמר רבי
חיננא בר שלמיא keivan d'sham'ah l'ha d'amar Rabbi Chinana bar Shlamya since
he heard what Rabbi Chinana bar Shlamya said משמיה דרב mishmeih d'Rav
הכל מודים בסיכי זוי ומזורי ha-kol modim be-sichi zavi u-mezorei
everybody agrees with these three implements. Now Rashi has two interpretations: either
these are various instruments for making fragrances or these are various instruments
for for weaving. But whatever they are they're certain types of professional
instruments and everybody agrees regarding them that they're worse than a כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto l'issur. Why? דכיון דקפיד עלייהו d'keivan d'kapid aleihu
since you're very careful with them you don't want to you know
you don't play around with them you don't use them for any
other purpose. You really, like they are, "Don't touch that, that's my
professional,
my professional thing, my professional tool." So in that case, מייחד להו
מקום, Miyachid Lehu Makom, you designate a place and basically it means
it's off limits. So there's certain types of professional tools which are
worse than כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. Kli Shemilachto L'isur. The things you don't
want anyone touching, and those types of things are complete מוקצה. Muktzah.
That category is generally described as מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס. Muktzah Machmat
Chissaron Kis. A מוקצה Muktzah because you're afraid of financial loss. But
even the financial loss doesn't have to technically mean like it's expensive.
It just means like I don't want anyone fooling with that. You
know, that's my thing, I don't want anybody fooling with it, I
don't want anyone touching it, playing with it, and so on. So
this is a special category of מוקצה Muktzah and that explains this
idea of the of the pounder, of the pestle, that even if
not worse than כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור Kli Shemilachto L'isur would be a
type of thing that you don't want anybody to touch, to use
for any purpose other than grinding spices.
Okay, can I be specific? In other words, no no no, I
mean is like, you know, I'm okay touching it, but I don't
want you touching it. So does it become מוקצה Muktzah for me
now? Like let's say it's my special fork, right? I only want
to use it but I don't...
That's a good question. That's a good question. I mean that gets
to a סוגיא Sugya about like מוקצה לעניים, Muktzah L'aniyim, you know,
מוקצה לעשירים, Muktzah L'ashirim, is it מוקצה לעניים? Muktzah L'aniyim? And whether
we do so. So there is a there is a סוגיא Sugya
about that, about whether if for the owner, you know, he would
use it but other people would, or vice versa. So it's a
good question and it's definitely discussed.
I will tell you by the way, well let me refinish this
and then I'll tell you an interesting story that happened to me
that relates to a case in the משנה Mishnah that's about this
question here. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: איתמר, Itmar, was
taught by רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Chiyya bar
Avin amar Rabbi Yochanan, קורנס של זהבים שנו. Kurnas shel zehavim shanu.
Our משנה, Mishnah, did I skip a line? No. Our משנה Mishnah
that allows using a hammer to crack nuts is not only a
blacksmith's hammer which is okay כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, Kli Shemilachto L'isur, but
something, you know, that you're not too מקפיד Makpid on. I mean,
you know, big heavy hammer, what's, you're not going to hurt it.
But even if it's a even if it's like a hammer for
a goldsmith, which you would use, you know, much more delicate, you'd
use to like thin out the gold. So that type of a
hammer you would assume you might assume that people don't want you
fooling around with it and using it for something else. You might
damage the hammer, right? It's a delicate instrument. Even that is allowed
to crack nuts. That's quite a big חידוש. Chiddush. So much, you
know, this concern about like professional instruments is obviously now getting smaller
and smaller according to this. And רב שמן בר אבא אמר קורנס
של בשמים שנו. Rav Shemen bar Abba amar kurnas shel besamim shanu.
Not only that, even a type of a hammer used for cracking
or, you know, making fragrances. Or they're in addition to the fact
that it might be somewhat like delicate and it's a professional כלי,
Kli, but also you don't want to use it for other stuff
because you get it שמוצד Shmutzed up and it gets the smell
of other things on it. And the whole idea is that it
be like pristine. So even that's you're allowed to crack nuts. So
the גמרא Gemara says: מאן דאמר דבשמים כל שכן דזהבים. Man d'amar
debesamim kol sheken dezehavim. If you allow the one for, you know,
for gold, for for spice, for fragrances, you would certainly allow the
one for gold. Because the one for fragrances you'd even be more
careful with. מאן דאמר של זהבים, Man d'amar shel zehavim, but if
you allow the gold the hammer for gold, אבל דבשמים קפיד עלייהו,
aval debesamim kapid alaihu, but you would not allow necessarily the one
used for fragrances. That would be something that you would not want
to be used for anything else. So, so actually it's quite fascinating.
I mean you would have thought that certainly I mean this thing
for spices and this thing for gold, even though we don't know
the exact, you know, reality it's describing, if you would I would
certainly have imagined that this is something you would not want to
be used for your nuts and you wouldn't want to fool around
with. And even here the last opinions are pretty broad. This idea
of something that you don't want anyone to touch is like a
really extreme case. So I did want to talk about an application
of that in the last case of the משנה, Mishnah, which spoke
about using a needle,
like a heavy needle for picking a lock if you got locked
out of your house. Even though it's a needle normally used for
like sewing sackcloth, you can use it to pick your lock. So
I remember once it was about 15 years ago on a שבת
Shabbat I got locked out of my house, my apartment, and there
was actually a פרום Frum locksmith in the community. So I I
went over to him and I asked him if he could come,
if you know, and help me get into my house, you know,
because it wasn't like he wasn't going to like unscrew anything, he
was just going to use like his pick, you know, whatever the
things that go into the keyhole and do it. So anyway, so
the the rabbi of the community, I don't know, somehow he got
involved and he said, "No, you can't do it, it's כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור." Kli Shemilachto L'isur. I said, "Look, first of all, even if
it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, Kli Shemilachto L'isur,
you're using it לצורך היתר, L'tzorech Heter, because there's no איסור Isur
in opening in picking the lock." And I said number two, it's
not a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור Kli Shemilachto L'isur because you use it
to pick a lock, picking a lock is not off limits. So
anyway it's a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. Kli Shemilachto L'heter. So anyway so
fine so I got into my house. But
if
you wanted to say it was a problem, it would have been
the problem that the גמרא Gemara here discusses that maybe it's like,
you know, professional tools. So professional tools you don't want to play
around with and use for anything. But okay but first of all
it's Michael's point he's using it. Number two he's using it for
their normal use, to open up a lock. So anyway, but that
is an interesting question about when כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור Kli Shemilachto L'isur
crosses the line to be
So what happens?
Is that מוקצה? muktzah?
Yeah, so that's a good question. Like I said, it's a good
question. I think that, you know,
to answer off the top of my head, I think that if
you're okay with people using it under certain circumstances and it's not
totally off limits, then it's okay, then it's not מוקצה. muktzah. But
if you want a more precise answer, I'll have to get back
to you. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואת הכוש ואת
הכרכר. ve-es hakush ve-es hakarkar. So you can also use like a
spindle or some type of like of a poker. These are various
things used in weaving, but I don't know, somehow they had like
a point at the top and you would use it to pierce
fruit or almost be like a toothpick. You can use that. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. פגה שטמנה בתבן. paggah she-timnah be-teven.
Let's say you have a radish—I think that's what a פגה paggah
is—no, I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi says it's a date. You have
an unripe fig. You have an unripe fig that you buried in
straw and apparently this was a way that you would do it
to get it ripe. It's I guess like nowadays they tell you
put fruit in a paper bag. You know that?
A brown paper bag. Right, I don't know why that works. Anyway,
so you put your unripe fig in straw and now the straw
is מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, because if it's straw used for feeding animals,
it's not מוקצה muktzah because you can feed your animals on שבת.
Shabbos. But if it's used for making like plaster with, which would
be you'd use for straw for your plaster, it is. That's why
for example the משנה Mishnah says that a pitchfork is a כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur because you're using it for straw, not
straw to feed your animals, but straw for other purposes—type of use
you would not be allowed to do on שבת. Shabbos. So here
you buried it in straw and it's מוקצה. muktzah. The straw is
מוקצה, muktzah, but the fig is not.
מותר לטלטלה. muttar letaltelah. So you can—did I skip a line?—וחררה שטמנה
בגחלים. vecharara she-timnah be-gechalim.
Or you have a type of a wafer that you buried in
coals to I guess help keep it warm. אם מגולה מקצתה—if im
megula miktzatah a little bit is exposed—מותר לטלטלה. muttar letaltelah. Then you
can move it because you grab the part that's exposed, you take
it out, and you're moving היתר hetter and the fact that incidentally
the מוקצה muktzah around it falls down when you remove it from
the hole is not a problem. ואם לאו—but ve'im lav if it's
not exposed—אסור לטלטלה. assur letaltelah. You can't because then to get to
it you'd have to move the מוקצה muktzah out of the way
and you'd have to directly move
מוקצה. muktzah. רבי אלעזר בן תדאי אומר Rabbi Elazar ben Tadai omer
says תוחבים בכוש בכרכר tochsim bekush bekarkar and here's the connection to
the משנה Mishnah because you talk about using these types of things
to pierce it, this spindle or this poker, this pointer. So even
if it's buried, you can go ahead and pierce into it, like
you know stick into the place it's buried a pointy stick. והן
מנערות מאליהן. vehen minaroat me'alehen. So basically you've got this radish or
what I keep saying radish, you've got this fig buried in מוקצה.
muktzah. You stick a stick in, a pointy stick in, you spear
it, and you pull it out. So you've never directly moved the
מוקצה. muktzah. You're always just pulling it out. Now the problem is
though as you're putting the spear in, the spear is pushing aside
the מוקצה muktzah right getting to the היתר. hetter. But that is
called טלטול מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. טלטול מן הצד tiltul min
hatzad means indirect moving of מוקצה. muktzah. And that is allowed if
it is done
לצורך דבר המותר. l'tzorech davar hamuttar. Meaning it is done because you're
getting to something that's not
מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, then incidentally in your getting to it, you're allowed
to push the other stuff aside. So I cannot go ahead and
like move the coals aside, but I can you know stick my
hand in here as you're piercing something in but stick my hand
into the coals as long as they're only sort of moving aside
incidentally, not sort of directly being moved, and I'm going for the
היתר. hetter. That's allowed.
Can I blow to get the straw away?
So blowing is a different issue. There are two ways basically which
you're allowed to move מוקצה. muktzah. One is
טלטול בגופו—that tiltul begufo doing it sort of like with other parts
of your body, kicking it, your elbow, blowing it. Right, that's one
thing which is allowed and that's even allowed even more than this
case. That's allowed even if you're just trying to let's say I
don't know get it out of the way or something like that.
Okay, or get it somewhere else. Then there's this which is you're
actually like sort of directly doing it with your hand or an
extension of your hand but it's being pushed away incidentally. And that's
allowed—that's טלטול מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. And that's allowed when you're
going for a non-מוקצה muktzah item. Okay, so you can imagine that,
you know, you got I don't know something stuck behind
a ספר sefer you want is behind—this happens to me sometimes like
we put stuff on our shelves. So you know you've got like
your wallet or whatever on your shelf and you got a ספר
sefer there, right? So you go in for the ספר, sefer, you
pull out the ספר sefer and by pulling it out it pushes
aside the wallet or whatever it is, that would be okay.
But you're saying you could have just used your elbow to move
the wallet and then get to the ספר? sefer?
Yeah, you could do that too. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. אמר רב
נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן תדאי. halacha k'Rabbi Elazar
ben Tadai. We rule like that. למימר דסבר רב נחמן l'meimar desavar
Rav Nachman טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad לא שמי טלטול. lo
shemei tiltul. So this is what the גמרא... Gemara... So this is
what it's defined as, this is the category of טלטול מן הצד.
tiltul min hatzad. You see he holds that incidental moving is not
moving. והאמר רב נחמן, V'ha amar Rav Nachman, האי פוגלא hai pugla
מלמעלה למטה mil'mala l'mata and this is why I was thinking about
the radish. A radish מלמעלה למטה mil'mala l'mata if it's in the
dirt and it's there from top to bottom, meaning the wide part
of it is towards the top and the narrow part is towards
the bottom.
It's upside down?
No, a radish that's upside down. I guess so. Yeah, it is,
radish grows—well, you buried it. It's not growing, meaning where where where's
the—Right, so you
buried it upside down.
Are we talking about the same—I don't even know what—I'm not going
to draw this, this is not a what do you call—this is
not a—but basically it's like a V, right? So the wide part
of the V is towards the top of the dirt, it's towards
the top of the ground, and the lower is at the bottom.
That's upside down?
I thought it goes the other way, right?
Isn't it wider—the radish?
No,
it's—I think it grows that way if it's triangular, the wide
part is towards the top. Yeah, because I think the roots come
out of the angled part. Anyway, it doesn't matter. Here, it matters—here
it's already picked and this is how you're buried. Okay, so the
point is, if it's buried that way, as you pull it out,
the dirt is just going to collapse around it, but you're not
moving dirt to get it out, right? Because the hole—it just removes
simply from the hole. So if it's מלמעלה למטה, mil'mala l'mata,
שרי. shari. מלמטה למעלה mil'mata l'mala אסור. assur. From—but if it's reversed,
if the pointy top is towards the top, it's forbidden, because then,
if you imagine that the dirt has all fallen around it, to
get it out of the hole you have to make room to
get the wider bottom part out of the hole. It's interesting that
it's not even concerned about something like חורש choresh or בונה, boneh,
but presumably it's loose dirt, okay. But it doesn't matter, you're now
moving dirt to get it out. It's not just collapsing around it.
So that's טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad because you're moving something
permissible, you're directly handling the radish, but this is now moving. So
didn't he say טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad is allowed? So
הדר ביה רב נחמן. hadar beih Rav Nachman. Fine, he reversed himself.
And this is our basic principle that טלטול מן הצד tiltul min
hatzad is allowed. If you're moving the דבר היתר davar heter or
you're going for דבר היתר davar heter and incidentally stuff is being
pushed aside, that's okay. All right, so that was a connection to
the משנה Mishnah that spoke about these various כר וכסת. kar v'cheset.
Now, מחט שנוטל בה את הקוץ. machat she-notel bah et hakotz. You
can use a normal sewing needle to remove a splinter. Okay, שלח
ליה רבא בריה דרבא לרב יוסף. shalach lei Rava brei d'Rabba l'Rav
Yosef. So Rava the son of Rabba sent to Rav Yosef, ילמדנו
רבינו, yelamdenu rabbeinu, let our master teach us, מחט שניטלה חררה או
עוקצה, machat shenitlah chararah o uktzah, if you have a needle that
either its hole,
the top of it where the eye is, has been removed, חררה
chararah is like החור שלה, hachor shelah, or the point, מהו? mahu?
What's the halacha? Is it מוקצה muktzeh or not? אמר ליה, amar
lei, תניתוה, tenituha, we taught in our
משנה, Mishnah, מחט שנוטל בה את הקוץ. machat she-notel bah et hakotz.
You can use a needle to remove a splinter. וכי מה אכפת
ליה לקוץ בין נקובה לבין שאינה נקובה. v'chi ma ichpat lei lakotz
bein nekuvah l'vein she'einah nekuvah. What does the splinter care whether it's
got an eye in it or not? As long as it's—maybe presumably
if it's missing a point, maybe that's an issue because then it's
not so functional, but missing a hole, who cares? Now that's a
חידוש chiddush because you might have said that when שבת Shabbat comes
in to determine that this thing is a כלי, kli, you don't
just say does this have some theoretical use? You might want to
say is this for normal purposes still in the category of a
vessel? If it's still a vessel, then even if it could be
used for—even if it's מלאכתו לאיסור melachto l'issur it can be used
for לצורך היתר. tzorech heter. But something like this, which maybe when
שבת Shabbat began you wouldn't have normally classified it as a vessel,
you would say it's a broken needle, maybe you can't use it
even for לצורך היתר. tzorech heter. Now I do want to take
a moment to pause and say something important about הלכות מוקצה hilchos
muktzeh here, which people get confused. Okay, they think that the idea
of כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli she'melachto l'issur is like—you know,
it's the same type of a מוקצה muktzeh as I don't know,
מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס muktzeh machmat chisron kis or like sticks and
stones or whatever. But it's not true. Sticks and stones or things
that are מחמת חסרון כיס, machmat chisron kis, things you don't want
to move, other types of things, as we just said before, you
can't move for any purpose. Classic מוקצה muktzeh is completely off limits.
So there's a difference between מוקצה, muktzeh, which is also called sometimes
אינו מן המוכן, eino min hamuchan, which I think that basically the
idea behind them is hands off, off limits. Either because I own
it but I don't—you know, I have it but I don't want
people touching it, like this thing is disgusting like the oil lamp
that has all that's been, you know, whatever, it's just disgusting, מיאוס
mi'us or חסרון כיס, chisron kis, or because it's the type of
a thing that it never would have occurred to me to use
like a sticks and stones, right, that I didn't use as a
paperweight or whatever. That's one type of מוקצה, muktzeh, which is basic
like completely outside my realm, hands off, don't touch. Then you have
something which we're going to see in a minute when we turn
the page is different. It's called גזירת כלים. gezeirat keilim. Now practically
we call all of it מוקצה, muktzeh, but it's important conceptually to
distinguish it. Which is things that are normally things that you do
use on a regular basis, right? Your normal vessels that are regular
things that are used. Your hammer, your knives, your whatever. Sometimes they're
used for—sometimes they're used primarily for היתר, heter, sometimes they're used primarily
for איסור, issur, but they're within the realm of the things in
your house that are the normal things you use. Those are כלים.
keilim. There, within כלים, keilim, we say if it's מלאכתו לאיסור... melachto
l'issur... then you can use it for some purposes not for other.
You can use it to crack nuts, maybe you can't use it
to save it from being damaged. But that's a very radically different
because normal מוקצה muktzah you can't even move at all. Here you
can basically use it, or move it for a legitimate reason. So,
we are talking in the category כל הכלים, kol hakelim, right? We're
talking in the category of כלים, kelim, of normal household vessels. So
these types of things are fundamentally not מוקצה, muktzah, at most there's
some restriction about moving them. So you might have said, Look, once
the needle, even if it's מלאכתו לאיסור, melachto l'issur, at least it's
a כלי. kli. Once it doesn't have the eye of it, it's
not even a כלי. kli. It's like garbage. So maybe it really
is מוקצה. muktzah. So the answer's a funny answer. Ah, but you
can still remove a, you can still remove a splinter. Who cares?
Right? It might not be a כלי, kli, end of story. So
that's basically what the answer's going to be. Let's take a look
at the answer.
His answer was it still was a כלי kli because you could
use it for that, even though it doesn't have its normal use.
So, all right, we take a look. Let's keep going. So let's
see what the response is. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, איתיביה, eisivei,
I'll ask on this.
We have a משנה mishnah in כלים. kelim. מחט שניטל חררה, machat
shenital chararah, a needle that is missing its hole, או עוקצה, o
uktzah, or its point, טהורה. tehorah. It's pure, it's not a כלי,
kli, it cannot become טמא, tamei, and if it's טמא tamei it
stops being טמא. tamei. So you see in for laws of כלים,
kelim, for טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, it stops being a כלי. kli.
So maybe for laws of מוקצה, muktzah, it stops being a כלי.
kli. Okay, so that's a pretty good argument, assuming that there's a
similar definition. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye came
to defend the position of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Both אביי Abaye
and רבא Rava were students of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Okay, so
אביי Abaye came, says אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said, טומאה
אשבת קרמית? tumah a'shabbat karmit? You're coming to challenge, you know, to
throw טומאה tumah against שבת, shabbat, to say, to assume they're the
same?
טומאה כלי מעשה בעינן. tumah kli ma'aseh be'inan. By טומאה tumah it
says כלי מעשה, kli ma'aseh, you know, vessels
that are sort of fashioned. לעניין שבת מידי דחזי בעינן. l'inyan shabbat
midi d'chazi be'inan. By שבת shabbat it's just that it's usable. So
what does כלי מעשה kli ma'aseh come to exclude? So רש"י Rashi
says כלי מעשה kli ma'aseh means that it's still the way it
was made. Something that somehow is broken loses its status for a
כלי kli for טומאה. tumah. But for שבת, shabbat, as long as
it's usable, it still retains its status for a כלי. kli. So
according to אביי, Abaye, as long as theoretically I could still use
it, and again, it's not something that I actively am מקצה, maktzeh,
push away, it still would be a vessel. So a very broad
definition of כלי kli according to here, רב יוסף Rav Yosef and
אביי. Abaye. Let's see if the גמרא Gemara sticks with this. והא
נמי חזיא, v'ha nami chazya, and this is also fit, למשקא בה
קוץ, l'mishka bah kotz, to remove a splinter. למשקא בה קוץ. l'mishka
bah kotz. אמר רבא, amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, מן דכמותיך שפיר
כמותיך. man d'chamvatich shapir kamvatich. No, I'm sorry. The question from טומאה
tumah was a good question. It is similar. Why? מדלעניין טומאה לאו
מנא הוא לעניין שבת נמי לאו מנא הוא. mid'l'inyan tumah lav mana
hu l'inyan shabbat nami lav mana hu. It's pretty funny. He just
like restated the point before, but he says, yeah, that actually makes
sense. If it's not a vessel for one, it's not a vessel
for the other, which basically seems to be the point that I
was saying before, which is that it's not enough that in theory
you could use it. If you basically stop treating it as a
vessel, it's something you would throw in your garbage pile, then even
though in theory you could still use it, it stops being in
that היתר heter category known as vessels. So this is an interesting
question, whether מוקצה muktzah has a broader definition of vessel than טומאה.
tumah. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
מיתיבי, meitivay, I'll ask you, we have a ברייתא, braita, תוספתא tosefta
in כלים kelim that directly addresses the שבת shabbat issue. מחט, machat,
a needle, בין נקובה בין שאינה נקובה, bein nekuvah bein she'einah nekuvah,
whether it has an eye or not, מותר לטלטלה בשבת. mutar l'taltela
b'shabbat. It's okay to move on שבת. shabbat. ולא אמרו נקובה, v'lo
amru nekuvah, and the need for it to have an eye, was
only said אלא לעניין טומאה בלבד, ela l'inyan tumah bilvad, only for
טומאה. tumah. So this seems to be a direct proof to אביי
Abaye and רב יוסף Rav Yosef that you have a broader definition
of כלי kli for מוקצה muktzah purposes.
So תרגמה אביי אליבא דרבא. targema Abaye aliba d'Rava. So אביי Abaye
came and interpreted it according to רבא, Rava, meaning, yes, personally that's
a great support to me. But if I were רבא, Rava, here's
how I would
deal with this challenge. I would say the following: בגולמי עסקינן. b'golmei
askinan.
We're talking about a yet unfinished needle. זימנין דמימליך עלייהו ומשוי להו
מנא. zimnin d'mimlich aleihu u'mashvei lehu mana. Sometimes you want to make
it into a vessel. Meaning, if you have a difference between when
it breaks or when it never had an eye in it. If
you have a needle that never had an eye, although normally people
would make an eye, and for טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah you might
say it's not totally finished, and a normal needle has an eye.
For שבת shabbat we could say it's enough of a vessel because
you might want to keep it this way, and you might want
to set aside some needles without eyes in them for doing things
like removing splinters. Okay? So I still admit there's a difference between
שבת shabbat and טומאה, tumah, but in this realm where it's not
broken, it just maybe isn't completely totally finished. That might be enough
for שבת shabbat if it's still functional, but not enough for טומאה.
tumah. But if it's broken, it's a different story. אבל היכא דניטלה
חררה או עוקצה, aval heicha d'nitalah chararah o uktzah,
but if its eye or its point has been removed, then it's
a broken... then אדם זרקה לבין גרוטאות, adam zarkah l'vein gruta'ot, then
you just throw it into your scrap metal. a pile. Okay, and
therefore it is going to be not. So basically the end, the
upshot of this is everybody has to admit that it's not an
identical definition of a vessel for טומאה וטהרה Tum'ah v'Taharah as it
is for מוקצה. Muktzah. מוקצה, Muktzah, its functionality as long as it's
somewhat functional still allows it to be a vessel. By the way,
we're going to see that later about vessels that break, and the
broken parts might still be considered not מוקצה Muktzah if they're somewhat
usable. Okay, so there is, here's the important thing though to realize,
as I said, there is a fundamental importance for מוקצה Muktzah of
defining something as a כלי. Kli. If it's a vessel, it's not
like sticks and stones, not garbage, it's a vessel, and it's not
something you actively push away, like מיאוס Mius or חסרון כיס, Chisaron
Kis, then it's outside of the, out of normal מוקצה. Muktzah. Normal
מוקצה Muktzah means you can't touch it at all. At most, it
is a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, Kli she'melachto l'isur, and maybe you can't
move it for certain purposes, yet for other purposes you definitely can.
So it's very important to get something into the כלי Kli category.
How do we define כלי? Kli? Do we define it by טומאה
וטהרה Tum'ah v'Taharah or differently? So here the גמרא Gemara saying everybody
agrees not exactly the same. Okay, it might now, one
difference, the smaller difference to say, it could be that if you
have a vessel that's not totally complete, like a needle that hasn't
had the eye put in yet, since maybe sometimes you would leave
it that way, that would be good enough before שבת, Shabbos, because
in the end, maybe this would be the way you'll have this
needle and use it as a general thing. For טומאה Tum'ah it
has to be totally complete. That's רבא's Rava distinction. אביי Abaye and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef are even more radical. They even say even
if it is a needle, and even if it breaks, it still
retains its status of a כלי Kli for מוקצה. Muktzah. Okay, so
that's going to be an ongoing question about what is the definition
of כלי Kli for מוקצה. Muktzah. Here we see it certainly is
to some degree broader than it is by טומאה וטהרה. Tum'ah v'Taharah.
Yes?
If you have a כלי Kli that's like a hammer that you're
not allowed to use for hammering a nail, but you can use
it to hammer a nut? Right. Does that mean you could only
move it if you have to hammer a nut, or because it
you can hammer a nut, you can move it around if you
need to get...?
Okay, so that's what we're going to talk about. There are three
types of moving within כלים, Keilim, non-מוקצה Muktzah but כלים, Keilim, כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור. Kli she'melachto l'isur. One is לצורך גופו, L'tzorech gufo, hammering
a nut, doing something היתר Heter with it. One is לצורך מקומו,
L'tzorech mekomo, you need its space. You know, it's on the table
and you need to set your table.
Those are, the second one is going to be debated but we
rule the second one is okay. And the third, which is the
one thing you're not allowed to do, is מחמה לצל, Mechama l'tzel,
move it from, like, to protect it. It's out in the yard,
it's raining, it's going to get damaged. Okay, because that's seen somehow
as that like there's not, well, I'll talk about it more in
a minute, but presumably the explanation is because there it's like you
care about it qua hammer. This is my hammer and I don't
want it to be damaged. So then you're really relating to it
as a, as a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. Kli she'melachto l'isur. If you're
using it to crack nuts, you're relating to it as a nutcracker.
If you're moving it, you're getting it off the table, you're not
relating to it as anything other than an annoyance. Okay, but to
sort of relate to it as your, as a classic hammer, that's
the problem and that's the מחמה לצל Mechama l'tzel and that's the
one thing you can't do.
But there's no differentiation? In other words, if I crack, I want
to crack my nut, you know, then maybe I can take it
to wherever my nut is, but if I want to get it
off the table, I may need to just move it as, you
know, to like the nearest thing away.
No, no. Once you have it in your hand you can put
it down anywhere. I thought you were going to ask another thing,
which is if your hammer is out in the yard and it
starts to rain, it would be a good idea to find some
nuts you need to crack. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, אסובי ינוקא. Asuvei Yanuka. Now here this is going
to, this is really
a little bit off topic, we'll see how it connects in a
minute. אסובי ינוקא, Asuvei Yanuka, can you go ahead and like straighten
the limbs of an infant? Okay, this was some, the question was
is this considered a type of a רפואה Refuah or not? Now
we know that certain types of medications are forbidden because of concern
of like making, you know, that you'll come to grind your own
medications. רש"י Rashi says here since it's basically a physical type of
an activity and it's not really related to medications, the issue is
not the rabbinic prohibition of taking medications, the issue is... no, yeah,
something like that, like a rabbinic concern of like you're fixing the
kid. Obviously, I don't know, somehow you're, you know, you're, they do
something to to stretch its limbs or to smooth its limbs or
something like that. Not exactly keep, clear to me what you would
do. Okay, you're, yeah, like it has loose limbs.
But this is translated as as causing the baby to vomit, using
an emetic...
No, we're about to say vomit in a second. That's how I
translated the first thing, אסובי ינוקא? Asuvei Yanuka? That's not what רש"י
Rashi says.
רש"י Rashi says manipulated use...
Ah, so it wants to compare it to the next line. Okay,
that I don't know. רש"י Rashi says and תוספות Tosafot agree that
it's about something about about sort of like straightening its limbs, like
the, and so on. Let's take a look. What's the story? רב
נחמן אסר, Rav Nachman asar, Rav Nachman says it's forbidden. רב
ששת שרי, Rav Sheshet sharei, Rav Sheshet says it's allowed. רב נחמן
אמר רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, amar Rav Nachman, said Rav Nachman, מנא
אמינא לה, Mena amina la, where do I know it? דתנן, D'tenan,
we taught in the משנה Mishna coming up, אין עושין אפיקטויזין בשבת,
Ein osin apiktoizin b'Shabbos, you cannot do a purgative, is that what
it's called? Something that causes you to throw up. Okay, you can't
take a purgative on שבת. Shabbos. Now, you could say that that's
again the issue about
רפואה. Refuah. רש״י Rashi says that it's not actually a רפואה Refuah
issue, רש״י Rashi says
because throwing up is not a רפואה. Refuah. Why? Because he says
you're not throwing up because you swallowed something bad, you're throwing up
for the good Greek reason that you want to eat more and
stuff your face more. So, so, it's not a רפואה Refuah issue.
You're not doing it for healing, you're just doing it to stuff
your face. Okay, but nevertheless, you're not allowed to do it. Why?
Because again this is the way רש״י Rashi explains that it's again
this issue like מתקן. metakein. So maybe some things that are not
even technically רפואה Refuah somehow are in the מתקן metakein category and
maybe this is included. Now תוספות Tosafot points out that the end
of this משנה Mishna also speaks about straightening limbs of an infant
as forbidden. So תוספות Tosafot actually thinks that the proof is from
the end of the משנה, Mishna, not this purgative but the end
of the משנה. Mishna. So says that's my proof. רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet will say back no. התם לאו אורחא
הכא אורחא. Hasam lav orcha hacha orcha. That's not normal. You know,
crazy person wants to throw up to do this or special case
where the limb, straightening limbs, whatever that case is. That would be
something that's not normal. But here, it's normal, you know, it's the
normal type of way of taking care of the baby. If you
look at רש״י, Rashi, הכא אורחא, hacha orcha, the last wide line,
he says פירוק כמין שמאכילו ומשקהו. Peruk k'min she-macha'ilo u-mashkeihu. It's like
feeding him, giving him food, drink, it's like a normal type of
way of just caring for the infant and it's not seen like
somehow either a רפואה Refuah or מתקן. metakein. Okay, so אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, now what does that have to do with
us? ומנא אמינא להו, U-mena amina lehu, where did I get this
idea? That now we talk in our משנה, Mishna, מחט של יד
ליטול בה את הקוץ, Machat shel yad litol bah es hakoitz, that
you can go ahead and take a needle to remove a splinter.
So you see again, it's not a concern of medicines, it's not
סמנים, sammanim, and it's not אסור assur because of like מתקן. metakein.
Doing types of normal types of care of the body is the
basic point is not מתקן. metakein. Okay, because you can remove splinters.
ורב נחמן, Ve-rav Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman would say, התם פקיד.
Hasam pakid. There the splinter is like held in the body. It's
not a part of the body, so you're removing something foreign, you're
not fixing the body, you're removing something that's not part of the
body. הכא לא פקיד. Hacha lo pakid. Here, it's not like something
is being held in the body. It's just straightening of the limbs,
and therefore it really is like you somehow are fixing the body.
So he says that it would still be forbidden, but the more
lenient position is, you know, these are just normal care of the
body and it's not a problem. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
קנה של זיתים, Kaneh shel zeitim, we're again talking about things that
are various vessels that are used for איסור issur purposes. Can you
use, what can you use them for? So you've got a stick
that is used for turning over olives that are in a barrel,
you know, to wait till they sort of, you know, moisten a
little bit or something in order that they're ready to be pressed.
So this stick, אם יש קשר בראשו מקבל טומאה. Im yesh kesher
berosho mekabel tumah. If it's got a knot towards the top of
it, like you know, a like I don't know, somehow a knot
in the wood, or some type of a bulb, then it becomes,
can become טמא. tamei. We'll see why in a minute. ואם לאו
אין מקבל טומאה. Ve-im lav ein mekabel tumah. And if not, it
does not become טמא. tamei. בין כך ובין כך ניטל בשבת. Bein
kach u-vein kach nital be-shabbos. Either way it could be moved on
שבת. Shabbos. Because again here's a clear משנה Mishna that says different
definitions of טומאה tumah and שבת. Shabbos. And therefore since it's a
כלי, kli, it's used practically, whether technically it's a כלי kli for
טומאה, tumah, in practice it's a כלי, kli, it can be used,
and even if it's צורך tzorech and even if it's מלאכתו לאיסור,
melachto l'issur, you can use it לצורך היתר. l'tzorech heter. Okay, so
let's see why it's why it might be not טמא. tamei. אמאי?
Amai? Why even if it has this sort of knot in it
is it טמא? tamei? פשוטי כלי עץ הם. Pshutei klei etz hem.
It is a vessel, it is a wooden vessel that has no
receptacle. ופשוטי כלי עץ אינם מקבלים טומאה, U-pshutei klei etz ein mekabelin
tumah, and wooden vessels which have no receptacle do not become טמא.
tamei.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why don't they become טמא? tamei? דומיא דשק.
Dumya desak. Because when the תורה Torah talks about vessels that are
טמא, tamei, it mentions a sack and it mentions wood vessels. So
the same way a sack has a receptacle, wood vessels have to
have a receptacle. That's one of the laws of vessels to become
טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא משמיה דרב נחמן בדומיא
דשק בעינן. Tana mishmeih de-rav Nachman be-dumya de-sak ba'inan. So תני משמיה
דרבי נחמיה, Tani mishmeih de-rabbi Nechemya, we talk in the name of
רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, בשעה שמהפך בזיתים הופכו ורואה בו. Besha'ah shemehapech
bezeitim hofcho vro'eh bo. When you turn over the olives, somehow the
fact that it's got this bulb or knot in the top catches
some of the olive oil and you take it out and you
look at it and you can see the olive oil and smell
it and taste it and you see whether the olives are ready.
So therefore there is some receptacle that is made by the knot.
רש״י Rashi makes it sound more like the actual rod itself is
hollow, but because it's got a knot, somehow that knot means that
some of it gets caught at the top, right, it stops it
from being a purely, you know, you know, open at both ends,
so therefore some of it gets caught and it has a בית
קיבול. beis kibul. Now, it has a receptacle. Now this by the
way is is important. Even before when the גמרא Gemara was considering
comparing טומאה tumah to מוקצה, muktzah, that was when something wasn't טמא
tamei because it was basically not a כלי. kli. Here we know
that it's a technical point. We know that you could have wooden
vessels that are a כלי kli that are not מוקצה, muktzah, like
a fork, you know, or toothpick or whatever, things that are totally
used for good purpose, but they are not necessarily not מוקצה, muktzah,
but they are not טמא. tamei. Because there's a special technical requirement
that a wood vessel is only טמא tamei if it has a
receptacle. Okay, so that the גמרא Gemara knows, it's clear in the
משנה, Mishnah, should not make it different for מוקצה muktzah purposes. The
earlier discussion was not this technical thing of a receptacle but was
a basic issue of saying that it stops being a vessel and
maybe that we would compare טומאה tumah and מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues, and here we get—we're going to get
to the heart of this whole category of כלים. keilim. Let's take
a look. רבי יוסי אומר כל הכלים ניטלין. Rabbi Yose omer kol
hakeilim nitlin. You could actually move all vessels חוץ מן המסר הגדול
ויתד של מחרישה, chutz min hamassar hagadol vehayated shel machareisha, except for
like a huge saw, like you know like you got like a
huge, you know, I don't know, what's it called, like not a
hacksaw. Is it a hacksaw? What are those big things like you
know sometimes even need two people, you know, to work on it?
Or a peg of a for the for plowing, for making furrows.
So those are the types of things which are you know real
work vessels for maybe things that are really like חסרון כיס cheisaron
kis and those are the things that are like off limits. But
otherwise, anything really can be moved. Okay, so seems to be—so let's
see how what the גמרא Gemara how the גמרא Gemara describes this
position. Let's take a look.
Let's see. Right. רש"י Rashi says כל הכלים kol hakeilim ניטלין—קפיד לא
ומייחד להם מקום, like we said before about the professional vessel. So
אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, האי אוכלא
דקצרי hai uchla dekatzri כיתד של מחרישה דמי. ke-yated shel machareisha dami.
There are other things that are in this category of things that
are מוקצה muktzah even if they're כלים keilim and can't be moved.
Like אוכלא דקצרי, uchla dekatzri, which רש"י Rashi says is—is that it's
a type of
a—קצרי katzri means like launderers, and רש"י Rashi says it's a type
of a metal basket with holes in it that they would use
either to, you know, to get the clothes—you know, either to sort
of get water on the clothes and it would be like a
basket the water would come out because it's got holes, it's like
a network, or because a latticework, or that they would burn incense
under it and it would get the clothes smelling nice. Okay, but
again, that's a special vessel that nobody would want to use for
anything else.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, חרבא דאושכפי, charva de-ushkafi, similarly a knife used
by
like butch—אושכפי ushkafi which is, oh right, which is used by like
leather makers.
וסכינא דאשכבתא, vesakina de-ashkavta, or a butcher knife, דחצינא דנרגא, de-chatzina de-nargi,
and
a—this is something about carpenters, right, a plane of carpenters, you know
things that they whatever. So כיתד של מחרישה דמי. ke-yated shel machareisha
dami. Also these are off limits. So this basically seems to be—Right.
It basically seems to be the point we're making before. There are
things that are כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur, those you can
move with לצורך גופו. tzorich gufo. There are some things that are
real מוקצה, muktzah, these sort of very expensive, you know, types of
professional things that you don't want anybody using for any other purpose.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues and here we introduce the
history of this thing, which is quite unusual that we get a
little bit of a history discussion. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught. Where are we?
בראשונה היו אומרים: barishona hayu omerim: שלושה כלים ניטלין בשבת. sheloshah keilim
nitlin beshabbat. You can only move three vessels on Shabbat. מקצוע של
דבילה, miktzoa shel deveilah, the knife used for cutting this thing of
like
pressed—I forget if it's dates or figs.
Figs, thank you, pressed figs.
וזוהמא ליסטרון של קדירה, vezuma listeron shel kedeira, some type of a
vessel used for removing the froth off
of a pot. וסכין קטנה שעל גבי השולחן, vesakin ketana she'al gabei
hashulchan, and your little knife that you use on the table. So
those were the only things—vessels, otherwise you couldn't move any vessel on
Shabbat. It was crazy! How do you get along? But first of
all, and you know you say, well first of all, you can
use your knife. What about your fork? What about your spoon? So
forks basically were only invented in like the 12th, 13th century, believe
it or not. People used their hands. Okay, I mean obviously you
use a fork to like I don't know turn something over on
the fire, but in terms of a table,
it was just your hands.
Exactly, because the whole concern about salt on your hands and מלח
סדומית melach sedomit is because the meat was preserved with salt and
because you would handle the stuff directly with your hands. That's exactly
correct. So anyway, so they would have
a—so—and spoons, now how about spoons, right? So תוספות Tosafot says that
presumably we don't mean things that have—are like receptacles, like you can
use—presumably you could have cups and plates and spoons, okay, those types
of things, you know, presumably they never forbade. But other types of
things, you know, everything else, only these were the only three that
they allowed, which is crazy! You could barely start—can move anything, not
touch but move anything. So we're going to see in a minute
that this was a reaction to widespread חילול שבת. chillul Shabbat. They
really wanted to push things the other way and wanted to get
people not handling vessels because vessels start bringing you into the world
of, you know, activity and of action and of מלאכה. melachah. So
well, okay, so this didn't stay this way. Originally they said no
vessels except these three.
התירו וחזרו והתירו, hitiru v'chazru v'hitiru, then they allowed some more, then
they went back and allowed even more. וחזרו והתירו, v'chazru v'hitiru, then
they went back a third time and allowed even more. עד שאמרו
ad she'amru until they said... basically saying כל הכלים ניטלין בשבת, kol
hakeilim nitlin bashabas, like our משנה mishna begins: You can move all
vessels. Okay, חוץ, chutz, the only exception, like we find in our
משנה, mishna, מן מסר הגדול ויתד של אחרי המחרשה, min masar hagadol
veyased shel acharei hamachresha, like this big saw and the peg of
the plowing, okay, because basically except for this category of professional vessels
which nobody wants to touch. So this basically and this is what
I said, the key about this is, this is גזרת כלים. gezeiras
keilim. These are not things that are מוקצה, muktzah, these are not
things that are pushed away and out of your use, these are
just regular vessels and basically what we're talking about is a special
גזירה gezeira which is not related to the basic מוקצה muktzah category,
that first said all vessels were off limit, then said all vessels
are okay except for a tiny handful which are sort of like
professional and, you know, מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס. muktzah machmas cheisron kis.
And but within those that are okay, we said if it's primarily
used for איסור, issur, then there are some limits. Okay, so again,
not מוקצה, muktzah, again, a הלכה halacha we call it all מוקצה.
muktzah. But to get you the right conceptual model, this isn't מוקצה,
muktzah, this is כלים. keilim. כל הכלים Kol HaKelim are okay, okay,
except for, like a small number and כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemilachto
l'issur there are some restrictions on, but it started in the opposite
direction. It started that they were all off limits. And now we're
going to talk about yes, Justin?
Just מוקצה muktzah in general, the whole מוקצה muktzah category, the whole
מוקצה muktzah is rabbinical, right?
Yeah, although there is an opinion in the beginning of ביצה Beitzah
that aspects of it are דאורייתא d'Oraisa but we don't rule that
way.
And the rabbinical is as some sort of fence to...
Okay, so why is... what is the purpose of the category of
מוקצה muktzah is a good question. Different things. There's a whole discussion
in ראשונים Rishonim why, the simple answer is like from the מן,
mann, והכינו את אשר יביאו, veheichinu es asher yaviu, that the idea
that you prepare for שבת. Shabbos. So only are the things that
are prepared and set aside and things so we mean assume most
your things you implicitly would be using for שבת, Shabbos, but things
that are not that are sort of pushed away that would not
you would not have thought to use, those are not relevant to
the שבת Shabbos world. So that's way of one understanding it just
an idea of מן המוכן. min hamuchan. רמב"ם Rambam says there are
other reasons given. רמב"ם Rambam says for people that don't work during
the rest of the week, what makes שבת Shabbos different than the
rest of the week, so there has to be some restrictions, you
know, some say it's a concern that it'll come lead to carrying
if you move around too many things you might come to carrying
them. But anyway the simplest explanation is just it's not מן המוכן.
min hamuchan. Here, by when we're talking about כלים, keilim, not מוקצה,
muktzah, the issue seems to be as we're going to see, that
a concern about
widespread חילול שבת chilul Shabbos that we have to basically, you know,
make שבת Shabbos radically different and get your hands off of these
types of things. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says. What does this
mean, מאי mai התירו וחזרו והתירו וחזרו והתירו? hitiru vechazru vehitiru vechazru
vehitiru? What were all these various stages of making more and more
permissible? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye,
התירו דבר שמלאכתו להיתר. hitiru davar shemilachto l'heter. First they said any
vessel that's used for normal היתר heter purposes is allowed because originally
they just said like a fork, you know, one or two things.
Here they said no, anything for normal use for normal היתר heter
purposes is allowed. לצורך גופו, letzorech gufo, if you're using it for
its own sake, to do something with it. וחזרו והתירו, vechazru vehitiru,
then that was stage number one. Stage number two is דבר שמלאכתו
להיתר לצורך מקומו. davar shemilachto l'heter letzorech mekomo. You can move that
type of thing even if you're not using this object just to
just because you need its space. Okay, that but again we're only
talking about מלאכתו להיתר. milachto l'heter. וחזרו והתירו, vechazru vehitiru, and then
stage three is דבר שמלאכתו לאיסור, davar shemilachto l'issur, even if it's
used for איסור issur purposes like your hammer,
לצורך גופו אין לצורך מקומו לא. letzorech gufo in letzorech mekomo lo.
Okay, and ועדיין בידו אחת אין בשתי ידיו לא, ve'adayin beyado achas
in bishtei yadav lo, and even at that stage they were only
allowing you to move something like with one hand and not to
move something with two hands, maybe that's greater effort and that's more
weekday-like. עד שאמרו, ad sheamru, and then this is the final stage
number four, כל הכלים ניטלין בשבת, kol hakeilim nitlin bashabbos, you can
move anything ואפילו בשתי ידיים va'afilu bishtei yadayim even with two hands.
So according to אביי Abaye by the end of the day, אביי
Abaye basically is pretty strict because he says a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemilachto l'issur cannot be used because you need the space, because
you got to get it off the table. Only a כלי שמלאכתו
להיתר kli shemilachto l'heter can be moved because you need the space.
And might be according to him even a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli
shemilachto l'heter you can't move מחמה לצל, mechama l'tzel, you can't move
to protect it. So his position is one degree stricter in each
category than our halachic position. כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemilachto l'heter he
doesn't let you use to move to protect and כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemilachto l'issur he doesn't let you move to get it off
the table. רבא's Rava going to disagree and we rule like רבא.
Rava. אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, רבא Rava said to him
מכדי, michdi, one minute, let's see. התירו קתני, hitiru katani, once it
says permissible, made it permissible, מה לי לצורך גופו מה לי לצורך
מקומו? ma li letzorech gufo ma li letzorech mekomo? What do I
care whether you're using it to crack nuts, whether you're using it
for its own sake, whether you're using it because you need the
space? Which is like a pretty funny argument. What he's really saying
is that I don't see why halachically we should distinguish between those
two. אביי Abaye obviously thought that we should. אלא אמר רבא, ela
amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava says, התירו, hitiru,
stage number one, when they made more things permissible, was דבר שמלאכתו
להיתר. davar shemilachto l'heter. Anything that's normally used for היתר, heter, you
can totally move, בין לצורך גופו... bein letzorech gufo... גופו בין לצורך
מקומו. gufo bein letzorech mekomo. Whatever reason you needed to use it
because you need to you need it for its own use you
need its space. That was stage number one מלאכתו להיתר melachto leheter
is totally okay. וחזרו והתירו vechazru vehitiru stage number two מחמה לצל
mechama letzell that not only that we'll even let you move the
object to protect it from being damaged even though you don't really
need it just to protect it a מלאכתו להיתר. melachto leheter. So
we totally have now allowed מלאכתו להיתר melachto leheter even מחמה לצל.
mechama letzell. This is the way we rule that you can move
something to protect it if it's מלאכתו להיתר. melachto leheter. והתירו vehitiru
וחזרו
והתירו vechazru vehitiru stage number three דבר שמלאכתו לאיסור davar shemelachto le'issur
לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו. letzorech gufo uletzorech mekomo. Something that you normally
do for איסור issur like a hammer, that you can move. Again,
he equates גופו gufo and מקומו. mekomo. You can use it either
to crack nuts or because you need to get it off the
table. אין, in, that's yes. מחמה לצל mechama letzell no. The one
thing you cannot do with מלאכתו לאיסור melachto le'issur is move it
to protect it. ועדיין ביחיד אבל בשני בני אדם לא ve'adayin beyachid
aval bishnei benei adam lo and even there they were only allowing
something that could only be moved by one person. Something that requires
two people, again, אביי Abaye is one hand two hands as opposed
to רבא Rava one people two people. רבא Rava is much more
lenient. So something that requires two people they said no that's too
big of a weekday activity or
whatever until they came to the final stage and said עד שאמרו
ad she'amru כל הכלים ניטלים בשבת אפילו בשני בני אדם. kol hakelim
nitalin beshabbat afilu bishnei benei adam. Even everything can be moved even
if it requires two people and we rule like רבא Rava and
this is very important. So it means that if you have something
that is not one of these מוקצה muktzah in the sense of
hands off don't touch it but you have something that's a normal
type of thing you use under normal circumstances, a hammer or whatever,
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto le'issur. That type of thing you can
do anything with, get it off the table, get it you know
use it for היתר heter purpose. The one thing you can't do
is move it מחמה לצל. mechama letzell. So I do want to
say something about what falls in that category of כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemelachto le'issur which people are not aware of. Where would you
put something like pens and pencils and paper? So some people feel
like oh my god like that's a type of thing you you
know it's totally you do a מלאכה melacha with it. You put
it to paper and all of a sudden you know you do
a מלאכה. melacha. But the real הלכה halacha is that that's a
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto le'issur. It's a כלי. kli. Okay? So
basically when I was growing up we had a lock to our
back door that like the peg that moved the lever whatever has
broken off. And the way you would move it is you would
take a pen and stick it like into the little hole and
like you'd move the you know you'd move the bar. So you
could totally do that on שבת. Shabbat. If you have a pen
and pen and crayons in the way you could totally move them
לצורך מקומו. letzorech mekomo. Okay? So it's interesting people I think sometimes
react to like pens and crayons viscerally as like totally מוקצה muktzah
but really it's just like a כלי. kli. Yeah computer would be
I would say a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto le'issur. So and
that would be שני בני אדם. shnei benei adam. So you need
to move a computer out of the way or you need to
use your your computer to crack nuts.
That would actually be okay.
And we're talking about things let's say like a big chest which
need two people to move right? And then it's מיוחד למקומו meyuchad
limkomo then you can't?
No. I mean no, מיוחד למקומו meyuchad limkomo is more that
it's not because it's heavy מיוחד למקומו meyuchad limkomo it's more like
you don't want people touching it. I if you want to move
a chest or a couch I mean certain stage it gets to
an issue of sweating on שבת Shabbat and עובדין דחול ovdin dechol
but it's not a מוקצה muktzah issue. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara let's get let's just get to the end of the ב
bais of the דף. daf. Okay.
היתיביה
אביי. Heitivei Abaye. So אביי Abaye asked the same issue that we
had on the עמוד א. amud aleph. מדוכה medocha this pestle excuse
me not the pestle the mortar the thing that you put the
the spices in to grind. אם יש בה שום מטלטלין אותה ואם
לאו אין מטלטלין אותה. im yesh ba shum metalatlin otah ve'im lav
ein metalatlin otah. If it has the garlic in it you can
move it then it's like considered like you're basically moving the garlic.
If not you can't. So what's the problem? It's מלאכתו לאיסור. melachto
le'issur. So אביי Abaye said I might explain that it's a point
moving it to get it off the table but according to you
רבא Rava what should be the problem of moving it? So רבא
Rava says הכא במאי עסקינן מחמה לצל. hacha bemai askinan mechama letzell.
Yeah I also have a category that it's אסור assur if you're
moving it to protect it from the sun to the shade. היתיביה
Heitivei I'll ask you again just what we said like at you
know minute you
know yesterday or the end of yesterday beginning of today. ושוין שאם
קצב עליו בשר שאסור לטלטלו. veshavin she'im katzav alav basar she'asur letaltelo.
This idea of the of the pestle that you want to use
as an ad hoc cutting board. That after you've cut with it
on יום טוב Yom Tov you can't use it anymore because you're
done it's שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov allowance. So why is
that? It's מלאכתו לאיסור. melachto le'issur. You should be able to move
it. הכא נמי מחמה לצל hacha nami mechama letzell fine רבא Rava
would say I could say it's talking that you're moving it to
protect it מחמה לצל. mechama letzell. אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina
בימי נחמיה בן חכליה נשנית משנה זו. bimei Nechemia ben Chachalia nishnet
mishnah zu. This whole idea that we made everything אסור assur now
we're going to see the historical background was in the time of
נחמיה. Nechemia. You know עזרא נחמיה, Ezra Nechemia, והנחמיה vehaNechemia right? דכתיב
dechtiv because the verse says from נחמיה Nechemia בימים ההמה ראיתי ביהודה
דורכים גיתות בשבת. bayamim hahema raiti biyehuda dorchim gittot beshabbat. In those
days in those days I saw in Judea in יהודה Yehuda that
they were you know they were trampling in the you know in
the wine vats on שבת. Shabbat. They were ממש mamash doing real
מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbat. People were there was rampant חילול שבת.
chilul Shabbat. ומביאים ערימות umevi'im aremot and they would bring the like
you know the bundles of wheat. So there's rampant חילול שבת. chilul
Shabbat. So to push back we wanted to say hands off of
all vessels you know then that way the vessels is is what
you do to do your work. So hands off of all vessels
and we were and we were extreme in the other direction. Well,
okay, then it restored some balance. אמר רבי אליעזר Amar Rabbi Eliezer
קנים
ומקלות גלוסטרא ומדוכה כולם קודם התרת כלים נשנו. Kanim u’maklot glustra u’meducha
kulam kodem hataras kelim nishnu. That and we'll pick up with this
tomorrow, but the basic point is he says I'm going to show
you
three משניות mishnayos or ברייתות braisos that basically sound like they are
very restrictive of moving vessels, even vessels that are מלאכה להיתר. melacha
l’heter. Okay, one about sticks, one about like bars,
one about sticks, גלוסטרא, glustra, which we'll see is a like there's
a type of also a what's the גלוסטרא glustra again? Oh yeah,
anyway, whatever, some type of a of a bulbous top to a
to a bar to a like a bolt, and מדוכה meducha which
is our case about the mortar and the pestle, all of these
seem to be very strict and the way I understand why they're
so strict is they were before we started allowing things. This was
at a time where all כלים kelim were off limits. So again,
the important thing to remember because the whole name of the פרק
perek is כל הכלים is that this is not your classic מוקצה.
muktzeh. Classic מוקצה muktzeh is completely off limits because in your mind
it's off limits and therefore you don't move it at all. These
are things which are your normal vessels that in a normal weekday
you would completely move and these are normal types of things you
use every day. Those things, you know, were fundamentally מותר muttar but
then there was a גזירת כלים gezeiras kelim that made them all
אסור assur almost and then because as a pushback and then slowly
slowly now basically it's all מותר muttar with the one exception that
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli she’melachto l’issur has some restrictions on it. Okay,
but that's basically very different than classic מוקצה muktzeh which is completely
אסור assur and we'll continue talking about כלים kelim tomorrow.
Are these are some of the things from yesterday though?